<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Naija Property Tips</title>
    <description>A simple yet classy theme for your Jekyll website or blog.
</description>
    <link>http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 02:29:12 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 02:29:12 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Buying Land In Nigeria</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Buying land in Nigeria especially in Lagos can be a very difficult decision to make. But in this post, I will highlight the 10 things you must check that will help you to make better decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Real Estate Consultant in Lagos, who has helped a lot of people buy and sell their land here in Lagos. I have come to really understand that before buying Land that there are some things you need to carefully consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FAQ question my clients always ask me first and I know you are also asking that question too is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Title does the Land have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know a man who bought land from the owners all papers were complete, and he went ahead to build and moved into it, only for him to receive a letter from the Government saying he should vacate the house as his house has been marked for demolition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He couldn’t believe his ears, according to the letter he was building what is not allowed in that area.
The government had already marked that area as an industrial area. So, building a residential home was not accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, most times it is not always about the land documents alone that you need to check before buying land there are a lot more and that is what I will be revealing to you in this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do follow me to the end and don’t forget to share this post as you do not know who needs this article…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##1. Location.
Location is the number one thing to consider when buying land in Nigeria. This is the foundation to other things you need to check.
The location will determine what value the land will be in the future because a land in a developed area will cost more than a land in developing area.
Another reason to consider location when buying land, is that you need to consider if the location of the land is fast attracting development.
No one will like to buy land that the location is slow in developing.
My advice when trying to consider location:
If you’re making an investment, don’t buy land with no resale value.
If you’re aiming on starting up a business, don’t buy land completely isolated from potential customers.
If you’re looking to build a house, don’t buy land you can’t build on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##2. Neighbourhood and Landmarks
Yes, you need to check who are going to be your Neighbours before buying land in Nigeria.
A lot of people make this mistake before buying land. The landmarks in that neighbourhood are the key to how fast an area will develop and the value the land will appreciate to.
You should try and look 5 – 10 years into that Neighbourhood and see what that area will become before buying land there.
Check to see if there any notable Government or Private project going on or already started to operate as this will tell you if the area will develop fast.
Any Neighbourhood you can find up to 5 World Class Landmarks weather in operation or still under construction then you are good to go.
For example, if the government or an individual decides to build a notable landmark like factory or university beside your land, the value of that land will automatically go up.
That’s why you need to take this into serious consideration before you buy land.
Another thing why you need to put this into consideration is to also help you check if at all you can cope with the development in the area when it finally comes for those who need to buy and build a residential home but if you are buying to resell then the development is going to be a big plus.
For example, some people might not be able to come with a plane always flying above their head why others love it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##3. Environment.
Checking the environment will help to know the land you want to use for housing purpose is safe to live around, as you don’t want to live in a polluted environment.
You need to consider the environment where the land is located and know how it is currently affecting those living there presently in order to guaranty your safety while living there.
Make sure there are no toxic substances in the area, like refuge disposals, poisonous smell from farms etc.
Also make sure that the area you are considering buying land from does not experience seasonal flooding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##4. Accessibility.
You might be saying that this is not important, but you will know how important to check if the land you bought is not accessible and you now have to beg your neighbour before you can access your land.
Always make sure that the area has good road network is accessible before buying land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##5. Security.
You need to know how secure the area you are planning on buying land into before buying land there.
Look to see if government has provided adequate security for that area. Also check to see if the community itself has a way of tackling security challenges.
You can also ask people leaving around there to know if the area is peaceful and does not get harassment from rubbers and hoodlums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security is a vital issue and must be considered when buying land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##6. Zoning Restrictions.
It is important to know the zoning permits of the area you are trying to buy land from as this will help you to know what government plan for that area is.
You will not be allowed to build a factory where government has already marked for residential building. You need to know this, so you do not have issues with the government in the future.
Even if the area is for residential building, know the kind of building the government permits for the area.
Building a sky scraper in an area where government says build bungalow is going to make you have issues with the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##7. Soil Quality and Composition.
Soil quality and composition will determine how you will build your new house or your new factory.
It will tell you the kind of additional money you will spend on the land when the time comes. It will tell you if you will need to do any land filling.
When it comes to building, soil composition can impact:
Cost of building foundations
The number of earthworks required
Stability and land retention&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##8. Size of the Land.
You need to also check to know if the size of the land corresponds with what the owner says it is.
The only way to do this is to get a surveyor who will come and survey the land and get the actual measurement.
Do not just assume because the owner says it one plot that it is one plot make sure you confirm.
Even though it will cost you money, but it is better you did and be sure of what you are buying.
That is why I recommend buying land from an estate this will cut away a lot of things and also make sure you are free from any Omonile Wahala (problem).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##9. Legal Documents.
After you have checked the above list, the next thing to check is the Legal documents that the land has, by this I also mean the Title of the Land.
When buying land, you must check to be very sure that the land you are planning to buy is genuinely registered.
A lot of people think that the best document to check for is the C of O (Certificate of Occupancy). but the is not good because any land with C of O in Nigeria only has 100 years to be used before the land comes back to the Government.
So, imagine that the land you are planning to buy has already been used for 30 years before now, that means you only have 70 years to use that land.
The main documents to check for is the Survey Plan, Deed of Assignment, Excision and Gazette.
This will help you to know if the land is under government acquisition or Free, you will also know what the land can be used for with the help of these documents.
Notwithstanding, you can still buy a land and register it yourself but make sure you are buying it from a genuine owner.
More information on Land Document&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;##10. Price Of Land.
I decided to leave this till you have checked to confirm other things I listed above first as they will determine what the price of the land should be.
For example, Land without any title can never be priced the same as Land with C of O.
Because each of this titles cost money to get, therefore the owner will definitely add these expenses to the cost of the land.
Also, the location and of the land has a lot to say about how the land will be priced.
So, with this information you can check to know if the owner is over pricing the land or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to use this opportunity to introduce PacificRim Global to you, we specialize in procurement and sales of real estates with great ROI in Nigeria, just tell us what you want and see it done. We are a property company you Can Trust. With years of continuous experience in Real estate consultation for clients both in Nigeria, across Europe and America;
Our Drive is only to help you make good investment decision whenever you think Real Estate. To learn more, visit our Facebook page https://www.facebook.com/pacificriminvestment/ or call &amp;amp; WhatsApp on +234 816 913 6023.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 02:28:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/land/2018/11/17/buying-land-in-nigeria.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/land/2018/11/17/buying-land-in-nigeria.html</guid>
        
        <category>buy</category>
        
        <category>purchase</category>
        
        <category>land</category>
        
        <category>nigeria</category>
        
        <category>lagos</category>
        
        
        <category>Land</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Investment Tips of The Day</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;have-a-budget&quot;&gt;1. Have a budget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself, how much am I willing to invest right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t be planning to buy land in Lekki when the money in your account is calling you to Ikorodu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-your-reason-for-investing&quot;&gt;2. What’s your reason for investing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decide your reason for investing. Are you investing for cashflow or huge capital gains in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you understand this, it will determine what you will invest in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;now-decide-what-you-want-to-invest-in&quot;&gt;3. Now decide what you want to invest in.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have decided to invest for capital gains, then you might decide to buy land in developing areas with potential for appreciation; somewhere like Ibeju-Lekki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are investing for cashflow, then you might want to buy an apartment and put it up for rent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get the point?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pick-a-location&quot;&gt;4. Pick a location&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;: Once you have decided what you want to invest in, you now have to decide on location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to buy land for capital gains, then you should be looking at areas that obviously have potential for appreciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to invest for rental cash flow for instance, then you should be looking to invest in an area that has high rental value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-am-i-buying-from&quot;&gt;5. Who am I buying from&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The importance of this cannot be over emphasized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You want to make sure you are buying from the right source, a major part of buying from the right source is conducting proper due diligence before making a commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this helps you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tag someone who 
can learn from this and please share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Courtesy: PacificRim Global
+234 816 913 6023&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good morning and have a blessed day 🙏🙏&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll-help&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s dedicated Help repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 01:10:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/invest/2018/11/17/investment-tips-of-the-day.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/invest/2018/11/17/investment-tips-of-the-day.html</guid>
        
        <category>investment</category>
        
        <category>land</category>
        
        <category>tips</category>
        
        
        <category>Invest</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Are You Tired Of Landlord</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/2018/11/17/are-you-tired-of-landlord.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://oladav58.github.io/centrarium/2018/11/17/are-you-tired-of-landlord.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
